Don Francisco Papers
Don Francisco Papers
1909-1965
Francisco, Don, 1891-1973.
8 linear ft.
Don Francisco was advertising manager for the California Fruit Growers Exchange, worked with the Los Angeles advertising agency Lord & Thomas, and from 1945-1956 with the J. Walter Thompson Agency in New York. From 1940-1945, he worked with the radio division of the Office of Inter-American Affairs in the U.S. State Department. Collection includes correspondence; material on the Office of Inter-American Affairs and advertising agencies; articles, reports, speeches, promotional materials, photographs, and scrapbooks.
148988
Biographical History
Donald ("Don") Francisco (1891-?) was an American advertising and public relations executive. A native of Lansing, Michigan, Don Francisco was born October 18, 1891, son of Will and Lillian (Burgdorf) Francisco. He received a B.S. from Michigan State University, 1914, his M.A. in 1923, and a PhD in 1949. After graduation he joined the Chicago office of the California Fruit Growers Exchange as a fruit inspector (1914-1915). In 1916 he was named assistant advertising manager (1916-1921) and as such was largely responsible for developing a large consumer market for orange juice. After six years advertising for Sunkist, he moved to Lord and Thomas as co-manager of the Los Angeles office. In 1924 he was named executive vice president of the agency and general manager for the Pacific Coast office, a position he held until 1940.
During the war he served as director of the Radio, Information, and Content Division of the Office of Inter-American Affairs in Washington (1940-1943) and then as Assistant Coordinator (1943-1945). He left the government in early 1945 and returned to New York to direct the Thompson Agency, where he served as vice president, director of J. Walter Thompson until his retirement in 1956. Francisco also served as a consultant to the State Department on national broadcasting and was on the Mass Media Committee of Enesco, as well as being a visiting lecturer at Michigan State University.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Don Francisco Papers consists of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, promotional material, published material, and scrapbooks.
Correspondence consists of both incoming and outgoing as well as some correspondence of others. Correspondents of interest include William Benton, Nelson Rockefeller, Albert D. Lasker, CIAA, UNESCO, Michigan State University, and various South American countries (Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Columbia, Peru, Uruguay). Correspondence of others consists of Albert D. Lasker's around-the- world letters to his family.
Subject files contains material concerning the California Fruit Growers Exchange, CIAA post-war plans, Florida Citrus Commission, Grocery Manufacturers of America, Michigan State University, USIA South American trip, and photographs and personal material.
Manuscripts consists of annual reports, articles, speeches, and outlines by Francisco as well as some speeches by others.
Promotional material contains material related to the California Chain Store Tax (campaign against), California Fruit Growers Exchange - Sunkist, Florida Citrus Commission, and J. Walter Thompson Company.
Published material consists of articles, books and booklets, and pamphlets about and by Francisco and by others.
Scrapbooks, all oversize, contain photos, clippings and letters relating to the California Fruit Growers Exchange, Boston Conference on Distribution, South American travels, and Crusade for Freedom, and to Francisco generally.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Francisco, Don, 1891-1973 -- Archives.; California Fruit Growers Exchange.; United States. -- Office of Inter-American Affairs.; United States Information Agency.; Advertising agencies -- United States.; Advertising campaigns.; Orange juice -- Marketing.; United States -- Diplomatic and consular service -- Central America.; United States -- Diplomatic and consular service -- South America.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Advertising.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming and outgoing
    - Argentina, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
    - Benton, William, 1945-1947; 1950 (Box 1)
    - Brazil, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Chile, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
    - CIAA (personal), 1944-1947 (Box 1)
    - CIAA (resignation), 1927; 1944 (Box 1)
    - Columbia, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - Don Francisco, personal, 1914; 1916-1917,; 1919,; 1921,; 1924-1927,; 1930,; 1935,; 1940-1941,; 1957 (Box 1)
    - Lasker, Albert D., 1921; 1924,; 1929-1930,; 1934,; 1938,; 1940-1942,; 1949-1952,; 1956,; 1958,; 1960 (Box 2)
    - Lord and Thomas, 1921; 1926-1928,; 1930-1931,; 1933-1936,; 1938,; 1940-1943,; 1945 (Box 2)
    - Lord and Thomas, Ltd.
      - Francisco luncheon acceptances, 27 Apr 1937 (Box 2)
      - Francisco luncheon declines, 27 Apr 1937 (Box 2)
      - Francisco luncheon congratulations, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Michigan State University, 1948-1949; 1954,; 1957 (Box 2)
    - Michigan State University Development Fund, 1956-1958; 1964,; undated (Box 2)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1940-1948; 1958,; 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - South American trip, 13 Dec 1940 - 9 Feb 1941; family letters (Box 3)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company, 1947; 1953,; 1954,; 1956 (Box 3)
    - J. Walter Thompson Agency, re. Francisco's resignation (Box 3)
    - UNESCO committee, 1946 (Box 3)
    - Uruguay, 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - General
    - A-C, 1914; 1921,; 1927,; 1948,; 1956-1959,; 1961-1964 (Box 3)
    - D-M, 1940; 1942,; 1944,; 1947-1948,; 1954,; 1956-1959,; 1962 (Box 3)
    - O-W, 1915-1917; 1919-1920,; 1933,; 1941,; 1943-1944,; 1946,; 1948-1949,; 1952,; 1954,; 1956-1959,; 1962,; 1964 (Box 4)
      See also Scrapbooks 3, 4, 5 and 9 for letters to D. Francisco
  - Of others
    - Lasker, Albert D., 1937-1938; around the world trip (Box 4)
- Subject files
  - California Fruit Growers Exchange, 1916-1917; 1919 (Box 5)
  - CIAA information activities after the war, 1943-1944; policies and plans (Box 5)
  - CIAA, miscellaneous, 1940; 1943-1945,; 1947 (Box 5)
  - Citation, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Course outlines, journalism (Box 5)
  - Diplomas (oversize), 1910; 1914-1915,; 1923 (Box 5)
  - Florida Citrus Commission, 1950-1951; 1953-1954,; 1958 (Box 5)
  - Francisco, Don, personal record (Box 5)
  - Glass containers, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
  - Grocery Manufacturers of America, 1943 (Box 5)
  - IBC-TV Film Network, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Idea book for advertisements and sales promotion, 1916 (Box 5)
  - International House annual report, 1965 (Box 5)
  - List of countries, islands, colonies, and states visited, 1937 (Box 5)
  - London visit, 1937 (Box 5)
  - Michigan State University (Box 6)
  - Numerology, astrology, etc, 1931-1933; 1935 (Box 6)
  - CIAA Radio, 1941; 1943-1944,; 1947 (Box 6)
  - Pacific Coast Displaced Persons membership #1, 7 Jun 1950 (Box 6)
  - Personal material, 1914; 1937-1938,; undated (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Post-war radio plans, 1945-1946 (Box 6)
  - South American trip, 1940-1941 (Box 6)
  - "Sunkist Story," Ambrose Stevens, tape recording (Box 7)
  - Short wave content committee (Box 7)
  - South America, 1941; miscellaneous notes (Box 7)
  - USIA, 1955-1958; 2 folders (Box 7)
- Manuscripts
  - Annual report, president, PCACA, 1924 (Box 8)
  - Articles by
    - A, E-F, H-I, L, S (Box 8)
    - Untitled, 1919; 1923-1925,; 1932,; undated (Box 8)
  - Lectures by
    - The story of Sunkist advertising, typescript (Box 8)
    - The Sunkist story, holograph (Box 8)
  - Sales presentations by
    - A plan for public information activities to be undertaken by members of the Grocery Manufacturers of America, 1944 (Box 8)
  - Speeches by
    - Add-Adv, 1918; 1928-1930,; 1935,; 1937-1938 (Box 9)
    - Am-Ap, 1929; 1932,; 1945,; 1948 (Box 9)
    - Ba-Co, 1917; 1924-1925,; 1936,; 1939 (Box 9)
    - Cu-Di, 1937; 1948 (Box 9)
    - Do, 1946-1947 (Box 9)
    - Do-G, 1924; 1928,; 1938,; 1940 (Box 10)
    - H, 1912-1913; 1930-1931,; 1938,; 1943,; 1950-1951,; 1956 (Box 10)
    - I, 1926; 1933,; 1941,; 1950 (Box 10)
    - M, 1931; 1938 (Box 10)
    - P, 1926; 1933,; 1938-1939 (Box 10)
    - R, 1942-1943; 1947,; 1954 (Box 10)
    - S, 1925; 1944,; 1948,; 1951 (Box 10)
    - T, 1925; 1932,; 1935,; 1942,; 1948 (Box 11)
    - Wha, 1923; 1924,; 1926,; 1931,; 1953; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Speeches by others
    - A-C, H-L, N, T, W, 1928; 1935,; 1939,; 1951,; 1953-1954,; 1957 (Box 11)
  - Speech outlines by
    - A-C, 1916; 1921-1924,; 1928,; 1930,; 1938,; 1948,; 1953 (Box 11)
    - E, F, L, N, 1921; 1923,; 1925,; 1938,; 1940,; 1949 (Box 11)
    - Oneida, Ltd., 1948; 1951-1953 (Box 11)
    - Ou-Q, 1924; 1932,; undated (Box 11)
    - R-W, 1920-1922; 1925,; 1928,; 1930,; 1932,; 1949 (Box 11)
  - Thesis for Master of Science in Horticulture, "The advertising of farm products", 1923 (Box 12)
  - "California 1934: A study of contrasts in a political campaign," Phillip H. Stevens, 1961 (Box 12)
- Promotional material
  - California chain store tax, campaign against, 1936; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - California Fruit Growers Exchange: "Sunkist", 1925-1926; 1947-1948,; undated; 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Campaign against California chain store tax
    - Discrimination vs. business (Box 13)
    - Public relations survey of Pacific coast industry chain stores (Box 13)
    - The story of two stores (oversize) (Box 13)
  - Florida Citrus Commission, 1950-1952 (Box 13)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company (Box 13)
- Published material
  - Articles about
    - 1912, 1916, 1936, 1938-1940, 1950, 1956 (Box 13)
  - Articles by
    - 1911, 1915-1933, 1937-1938, 1941-1944, 1947, undated, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - Books by
    - The Cooperative Advertising of Farm Products, 1924 (Box 14)
    - Distribution: A Look Back and a Look Ahead, 1949 (Box 14)
  - Books by others
    - Overseas Information Service of the U.S. Government, Charles A. Thompson, 1948 (Box 15)
  - Booklets by
    - Cooperative advertising of farm products, 1923 (Box 15)
  - Booklets by others
    - 14th report of the U.S. Advisory Commission on Information, 1959 (Box 15)
    - Labels, Advertising Dept., California Fruit Growers Exchange, 1918 (Box 15)
    - The Lasker story, as he told it, undated (Box 15)
    - What shall we do about the political situation? (Box 15)
  - Clippings about
    - 1916-1917, 1925, 1939-1941, 1943-1944, undated (Box 15)
  - Clippings about others
    - 1918, 1948, 1950 (Box 15)
  - Clippings by
    - 1920 (Box 15)
  - Clippings by others
    - 1945 (Box 15)
  - Pamphlets by
    - Advertising: an essential ingredient of democracy, 3 Oct 1939 (Box 15)
    - Distribution: A look back and a look ahead, 1949 (Box 15)
    - Does distribution cost too much? It may cost much more, undated (Box 15)
    - The force nobody knows: American industry, 1938 (Box 15)
    - Putting California's citrus on the map, 1917 (Box 15)
  - Pamphlets by others
    - The agent and the adviser / Albert D. Lasker, 1926 (Box 15)
    - A call for dedication to fundamentals in advertising / Albert D. Lasker, 1935 (Box 15)
    - The relationship of freedom of advertising to a free press / Albert D. Lasker, 1934 (Box 15)
    - Salesmanship in print / Albert D. Lasker, undated (Box 15)
- Scrapbooks
  - Photos and clippings of life of D. Francisco, 1909-1914 (Oversize 1)
  - Clippings by D. Francisco about California Fruit Growers Exchange, 1914-1920 (Oversize 2)
  - Articles of chain stores and letters to D. Francisco, 1936-1937 (Oversize 3)
  - Letters to and articles by D. Francisco, 1938 (Oversize 4)
  - Letters to D. Francisco, 1938 (Oversize 5)
  - Boston Conference on Distribution, 1939 (Oversize 6)
  - Boston Conference on Distribution, 1939 (Oversize 7)
  - Boston Conference on Distribution, 1939 (Oversize 8)
  - Articles on advertising, articles on D. Francisco, letters to and photographs of D. Francisco, 1920-1940 (Oversize 9)
  - D. Francisco on Latin American travels, 1938-1944 (Oversize 10)
  - D. Francisco on Latin American trip, 1944 (Oversize 11)
  - Articles by D. Francisco on distribution, 1944-1951 (Oversize 12)
  - Crusade for Freedom material, 1955 (Oversize 13)
  - D. Francisco, general, 1952-1961 (Oversize 14)
  - The Story of Two Stores, Undated (Oversize 15)